Guide to the Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad Company Records, 1860-1999 AIS.1982.23
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad, 1860-1999; VII.
  - Legal, 1850-1994; 5.
    - Merger of Norfolk and Western Railway Company and the New York, Chicago, and St. Louis Railroad Company, 1962 (Box 128)
    - US v. B&ORR, Grand jury investigation, 1980 (Box 129)
    - Pittsburgh and Lake Erie Properties (documents concerning property buying and selling, etc), Pittsburgh and Lake Erie Properties (files concerning selling off of land holdings, Engineering Files (Pittsburgh Coal company, agreements), 1912; 1993 (Box 140)
    - Mechanical Dept. - Transport Workers of America Cases ( MY -1 to My - 61 - A and G - 2 to G - 75), 1960s (Box 146)
    - Ex Parte 252, Incentive Per Diem Charges - Gondolas, 1970s (Box 163)
    - Time claims or Grievances, 1970s (Box 164)
    - Time Claims or Grievances (6476 thru 6672 - Time Claims or Grievances, 6628 thru 6639 - 1st Div. NRAB see file E502, 6640 thru 6641 - Time claims or Grievances, 6642 - See Board File A3T2, 6643 thru 6646 - Time Claims or Grievances, 6647 - 1st Div. NRAB et al, 6648 thru 6652 - Time Claims or Grievances, 6653 - 1st Div. NRAB, 6654 thru 6675 - Time Claims or Grievances, 1950s (Box 165)
    - Time claims or Grievances (18876 - 2nd Div. NRAB see A15 V117, 18877 thru 19025 - Time Claims or Grievances, 1960s (Box 166)
    - Time Claims or Grievances, 1957-1960s (Box 167-168)
    - 2nd Division Awards (NRAB), AV15V92 thru A16V113, 1960s (Box 169)
    - Agreement between P&LE and Yardmasters, Labor Agreements Effective 4/1/91, Mediation Agreements (UTU, BLE,ATDA,RYA,TCU & Telegraphers, Allied Services), P&LE Union Agreements, 1990s (Box 170)
    - P&LE legal case files including: 2373 (T. Sember), 2864, 6504, 5726 (Jas.Dugas), 4323, 3666,6294 (Roy E. Swagger), 4719 (Robert A. Blumling, 5619 (Russell C. Coates), 5710, M-969 (City of Pittsburgh Coates), 5711 (Pasq. DiRommaso), 5710 (Phillip Cheswick), 1980s (Box 171)
    - P&LE Files 6388 (J. A. Oliver), 6816 (Stan Lee Popinski), 5169 (Gary E. Harper), 5685, 5648, 5452, 6313, 5459 (Howard Humphries), 4815, 5633, 4130, 1980s (Box 172)
    - Time Claims Clerks, Clerical Rosters, Bonding Service Clerks, Vacation Clerks, Office Machines, Taxi Cabs charges, Payroll Information Clerks, Wages working conditions advertisement district, clerks agreements holidays vacations wages etc, Grievances of Employers, etc., 1980s (Box 173)
    - P&LE files: 8017 (R. A. Boyd), 7168 (J. Antovich), 7676 (C. J. Edowski), 7492, 6765 (H. E. Bethune), 6945 (Anthony Janocha), 7649 (Kenneth Gasparovich), 6944 (W. E. Gewin), 7885 (Charles R. Gooden), 6943 (Robert Dye), 1980s (Box 181)
    - 11551 thru 11599 (Time Claims or Grievances), 11600 (2nd Div NRAB A15V22), 11601 to 11602 (Time Claims or Grievances), 11603 (2nd Div NRAB A15V25), 11604 thru 11718 (Time Claims or Grievances), 11719 thru 11725 (Time Claims or Grievances), 1960s (Box 186)
    - Correspondence on railroad contracts, a bound report on elimination of Baltimore & Ohio Railroad crossing, 1934-1952 (Box 286a)
    - Index of early railroad contracts, 1875-1914 (Box 299)
    - Financial World Magazines 1930s-40s; Ads; American Railroad Car Institute Publication 1950s; correspondence, contracts regarding agreements between regional railroads; T&T publications--the American resistance movement; employee records; P&LE case against J.F. Kepler, 1909-1958 (Box 330)
    - Contracts between P&LE and other parties, 1877-1991 (Box 334b)
    - Records of securities and anti-trust litigation against P&LE, 1970s (Box 383)
    - Correspondence with PC&Y; sidetrack agreements; lease agreements; grade crossings; properties; National Industrial Recovery Act; accident report, 1910-1940 (Box 408a)
    - General notices; car men's agreements; 1967 Strike time claims; jurisdiction disputes; conference and grievances of Transport Workers Union of America, 1944-1972 (Box 435)
    - Political Action Committee files on accounting and expenses; lobby, and state rules and regulations; specific focus on Thornburgh administration, 1980 (Box 466)
    - Transport Workers Union of American claims, 1965-1968 (Box 481)
    - Regulations of Public Utility Commission; vending machine services contracts; organization of officials charts; contracts and agreements with Consolidated Rail Corp. and P&LE-Ashtabula Harbor Agreement; ICC locomotive inspections; relations with Dept. of US Government Presidential Advisory Committee on Railroads, 1928-1989 (Box 483)
    - Railroad toilet facilities reports; various train reports; time tables and schedules; operation of B&O trains over P&LE railroads; contracts and agreements with B&O; contracts and agreements with various companies and railroads; P&LE and PC&Y joint inspection and equipment maintenance; line service to Erie, PL&E, B&O, Cleveland, Pittsburgh, and Baltimore, 1928-1982 (Box 485)
    - Board of Directors meeting minutes; Penn Central Transportation Company reorganization proceedings; Mary Crowell et. al vs. Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad Company litigation records (court reports and bills, etc.), 1969-1974 (Box 486)
    - Damage suits and claims; injury cases handled by claims dept.; federal and state safety regulations (OSHA); taxes, assessments, and W-2s; inventions and patents; Federal Railway Administration safety standards; police reports; W-4s; increase and decrease of furloughs; blue flag reports; equipment dept. monthly accident reports, 1964-1989 (Box 487)
    - Reports to the office of Chief Engineer from the American Railway Association, Interstate Commerce Commission, Pennsylvania Railroad Association, Eastern Railway Association, General Managers Association; information regarding industrial supplies and equipment; PC&Y: Employee medical reports, 1960-1991 (Box 488)
    - Paperwork concerning restructuring (legal agreements, master agreement, creditor relations, investments, legal requirements), 1985 (Box 489)
    - Sale of Pittsburgh & Lake Erie to Bank of Mellon; standing agreements and contracts, reports of net worth based on property, past formal agreements relating to selling the company, 1976-1987 (Box 491)
    - Claims awaiting appeal; files of various railroad and transportation organizations; organization claims; district group advertisements and awards; vacation agreements for mechanical dept. and Maintenance of Way, 1980s (Box 492)
    - Annual reports to Ohio Department of Taxation (1991); Interstate Commerce Commission applications for construction approval; Who's Who In America lawyer directory; submissions for RR execs; Oliver Iron and Steel Corp purchase of riverfront property legal documents; inspection trips; file of Alfred E. Perlman speech to Newcomen Society; National Assoc. Railroad and Utility Commission; grade crossings; land purchases; Conrail agreements; increased freight rates and charges (1957); LE&E files, 1970-1991 (Box 493)
    - Claims, 1949-1973 (Box 494)
    - Legal notes to CSX regarding agreements with ARASA; pay; health services; 1990 review of labor and union agreements, 1990-1992 (Box 501)
    - Working, e.g., functioning contracts for lien agreements, lease, and loan with various companies and banks, 1938-1969 (Box 503)
    - Director of Labor Relations and Personnel, employee time claims and grievances, 1959-1960 (Box 504)
    - Legal dept. agreements, contracts, leases, General Electric, local Delaware court case (Bertram Field v. Henry G. Allyn, Jr. et al -class action claim); Coal Ventures inc., pre-acquisitions meetings and reports; Mellon Branch account activity, 1978-1993 (Box 505)
    - Employee legal documents and correspondence; debts, safety, service, violations, activities, discipline, 1986-1989 (Box 506)
    - Time claims and grievances (P&LE vs. various unions), 1950-1970 (Box 508, 510-511)
    - Shop maintenance standards (1986); multi-railroad agreements on car men, their helpers, and apprentices (1963); agreement between PA railroads and American Railway Supervisors Association (1957); master agreement for restructuring of obligations of P&LE (1985); various other multi-railroad agreements; Montour Railroad railway operating revenues (1927-1941), 1927-1986 (Box 517)
    - Report and recommendations of United Transportation Union study committee; various publications including testimony transcripts; report on trends of railroad construction costs; shipment conditions; research reports of Federal Railroad Administration; Annual Reports of National Mediation Board; Railway Accounting Rules; ICC Amendments, Rules, and Dockets; Constitution and annual report of American Short Line Railroad Association; Public Utility Law, etc., 1923-1992 (Box 532)
    - Bertram Field and Edward L. Franucchi v. Henry G. Allyn, Jr.; Finance Auditors report; Wheeling Dollar Coal leases and valuation; stock buying reports; securities firms, 1979-1985 (Box 533)
    - Articles of Agreement for P&LE, PC&Y, Y&S, and MCRR, 1920-1975 (Box 536a-536b)
    - Contract cards; A - G, 1880-1980 (Box 565-566)
    - ICC Hearing for B&O and P&LE featuring exhibits of routes, statistics, land valuations, rehabilitation, costs, savings, employees, departmental duties, switching studies, tax and capital stock information, proposed usage payments, explanation of valuation figures, etc., 1963 (Oversize 569-570)
    - Lake Erie & Eastern Railroad: ICC Bureau of Valuation land report with carrier's review, objections, and revisions, 1923-1926 (Oversize 580)
    - Report to ICC Bureau of Valuation by Pittsburgh and Ohio Valley Railroad, 1940-1952 (Oversize 581)
- Pittsburgh, Lisbon & Western Railroad, 1925-1945; VIII.
  The Pittsburgh, Lisbon & Western (PLW) Railroad was a short line that worked under the Youngstown & Southern Railroad until January 1, 1945 when it was absorbed into the smaller line.
  This series contains a small span of records from 1925 to 1945. They touch on financial and labor topics as well as the use of the railroad in the War Production Board under the Office of Defense Transportation.
  - Pittsburgh, Lisbon & Western Railroad accounting, Association of American Railroads bulletins; audits; social security; retirement; correspondence with oil companies; wage increases; state highway department, 1925-1945 (Box 442a)
  - Pittsburgh, Lisbon & Western Railroad; war production board forms and correspondence, Office of Defense Transportation notices and correspondence, American Railway Express bulletins, invoices, annual returns, 1925-1945 (Box 442b)
- Pittsburgh, McKeesport & Youghiogheny Railroad, 1870-1960; IX.
  The Pittsburgh, McKeesport & Youghiogheny (PM&Y) Railroad ran from 24th Street in Pittsburgh to Connellsvile, Pa., in 1882. The PM&Y followed the Monongahela River to McKeesport, Pa., then the Youghiogheny River to Connellsville, Pa.
  Within this series are reports and miscellaneous files for this subsidiary of the Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad.
  - Engineering Department - Budgets 1958-61, files regarding Pittsburgh, McKeesport & Youghiogheny Railroad, 1950s (Box 204)
  - Monongahela Connecting Railroad 100th Anniversary collection of pen and ink drawings; report book for Pittsburgh, McKeesport, & Youghiogheny Railroad; right of way deeds, 1870-1925 (Box 529b)
- Youngstown & Southern Railroad, 1900-1956; X.
  The Youngstown & Southern (Y&S) Railroad was a subsidiary of the Montour Railroad until December 31, 1946 when the Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad and Pennsylvania Railroad bought it jointly. In 1970, the Penn Central Transportation Company (successor to the New York Central and Pennsylvania Railroad) declared bankruptcy and the newly-independent P&LE acquired full control of the Montour and with it the Y&S. After P&LE's decline, the newly-created PL&W Railroad began operating the Y&S under lease on May 1, 1993, and transferred the lease to the Ohio and Pennsylvania Railroad, a part of the Ohio Central Railroad System, on June 14, 1995.
  Although its history spans 1904 to 1993, the materials in this series are scant and leave large gaps. What is present are meeting minutes, annual reports, the merger proposal for Montour and Y&S, and litigation involving the closing of Montour and Y&S.
  - Engineering Department - 1956 Zoning Ordinance; files on Montour Railroad and Youngstown & Southern Railroad acquisitions; main line switch; City Planning reports; crossings; property purchases; articles of agreement, 1898-1958 (Box 218)
  - Youngstown Suburban Railroad Co. minutes and record books, 1903-1925 (Box 350)
  - Annual reports of Lake Erie & Eastern, Youngstown & Southern, Mahoning State Line, and Montour railroads, 1949-1979 (Box 377)
  - Maintenance of Way agreements; P&LE news bureau releases; stockholder meetings; vendor brochures; published annual reports; Montour agreements; irregularities and disciplines; Youngstown Superintendent Association meeting notes and correspondence, 1960s-1970s (Box 379)
  - Laws and litigation of Montour and Y&S closings; filed complaints; police commissions, 1942-1968 (Box 385a)
  - Building costs booklet; daily locomotive performance records; valuation docket of Montour; train statistics of Interstate Commerce Commission; contracts; Y&S merger proposal; Bessemer & Lake Erie Railroad correspondence; policeman commissions; numerous loose blueprints, 1914-1994 (Box 516a)
  - Chief Engineer's Office correspondence concerning equipment and purchase orders, employee age limits; publication information; Youngstown & Southern Railroad Transfer Contract; physical requirements; matters of signals, transportation, and storage; test equipment; microfiches of interchange, 1932-1989 (Box 524)
  - Locomotive school study books and review questions; annual proceedings for various rail associations; port authority commuter rail study; authority for expenditure of Y&S Railway, AAR bulletins concerning claim work; "facts about featherbedding;" Montour expense book (1960); Montour balance sheets (1921-23); annual reports of P&LE, Mahoning, Beaver & Ellwood (1920s), 1940-1970 (Box 531b)
  - Youngstown Sheet & Tube general notices and switch agreements; Republic Steel general notices and switch agreements; USS general notices; car reclaims; Penn Central correspondence, 1970-1975 (Box 547b)
  - Freight car ownership logs; maintenance of equipment and freight cars; sale orders; leased car file; terminal building development; re- stenciled cars; car retirement sheets. Montour Railroad and Youngstown & Southern Railroad monthly reports of revenue freight cars, 1970-1990 (Box 552a)
  - Board of Directors meeting minutes, 1944-1979 (Oversize 575)
- Training Material, 1970s-1980s; XI.
  Part of the railroad record consists of training material in the form of audio or visual media, such as 16mm motion picture, 35 mm slides, 8 mm film, VHS, and audio cassettes.
  - Slides with audio: Blue Flag instructions, Car Inspector Cartoon, Box Car Doors, The Disablers, Maintenance of Way Safety, Tools of a Carman; Film: Personal safety, Coupling and Air hose, "Those vital ten minutes" (Box 141-142)
  - Slides with script (Burning Torch), Slides with no audio cassette (Trainmen Orientation), 8 mm film rolls 6 (Box 143)
  - Slides with audio (Hand tool safety, Signals #2, They Can't Stop, Air Brake), 1970s (Box 156)
  - Film (Couplers and Coupling), Slides without audio (Blue Flag), Slides (Hazardous Materials), 1970s (Box 157)
  - Carousel Transvue 80 slide trays and film reels pertaining to safety and training, 1980s (Box 519a-519b)
  - Various documents including Ohio Legislature; booklet on wrought iron (1960); equipment department file index; cassette tapes on Air Brakes; packet of color photographs from Aliquippa Southern Railroad (1981); aperture card; folder containing selection of blank P&LE and Montour Railroad forms and cards; photograph of railroad personnel, 1913-1980 (Box 564)
- Audio-Visual Materials, XII.
  - Photographs, 1886-1972; 1.
    The photographic images provide visual documentation of P&LE railroad activities during the early- to mid-twentieth century. Included is the work of nationally known photo-documentarian David Plowden. These photographs contain information not only about the P&LE, but also the various branch lines that, along with P&LE, were controlled by the New York Central Railroad System (1883-1968), and later by Penn Central (1968-1970). Besides railroad information, many of the photographs are devoted to non-railroad activities and scenes. This sometimes incidental information is found in urban rural scenes predominantly in western Pennsylvania's Fayette, Washington, Allegheny, Beaver, and Lawrence counties, as well as in some of the bordering counties of West Virginia and Ohio.
    The photographic formats represented in the collection are dry gelatin glass plate negatives, cellulose nitrate negatives, cellulose acetate, and 4x5 safety negatives. The images are universally of high quality both in terms of physical condition and aesthetic composition documenting industrial scenes along the railroad's rights of way as well as railroad facilities and equipment. The western Pennsylvania countryside is also featured in images taken for the proposed Lake Erie-Ohio River Canal in the 1940s. Also well represented are events such as river parades, celebrations in downtown Pittsburgh, as well as disaster such as wrecks and floods.
    The Archives Service Center maintains an item level inventory of the photographic portion of the collection that is available for on-site review. The photographic images are arranged by date and image number assigned by the photographers. Portions of the photographs have been made available online: http://historicpittsburgh.org/collection/pittsburgh-lake-erie-railroad-company-records.
  - Film, 2.
    - Rail Repair, 1933
    - Rail Repair, 1933
    - Test Shot by C. S. Zollinger Westinghouse Plant, East Pittsburgh, August 1946
    - Ashtabula; Foot of 23rd Street; W. Bridgewater, January 7-8, 1940
    - Extra Rail Laying, June 1937
    - Ballast Cleaner, July 20, 1931
    - Pittsburgh Power House, July 20, 1938
- Oversize, 1913-1981; XIII.
  These items are housed in flat files or wrapped in brown paper and tied. Generally, they consist of large ledgers, spreadsheets, meeting minutes, or blueprints.
  - Monongahela Connecting Railroad: Project envelopes for railroad improvements, 1966-1970 (Oversize 1)
  - ICC Hearing for B&O and P&LE featuring exhibits of routes, statistics, land valuations, rehabilitation, costs, savings, etc., 1963 (Oversize 2)
  - ICC Hearing for B&O and P&LE featuring exhibits of employees, departmental duties, switching studies, tax and capital stock information, proposed usage payments, explanation of valuation figures, etc., 1963 (Oversize 3)
  - Montour Railroad: Log of detailed traffic statistics, 1940-1943 (Oversize 4)
  - Montour Railroad: ICC Bureau of Valuation land reports and engineering reports, including blueprints, 1917-1926 (Oversize 5)
  - Montour Railroad: Reports of waybills received from various companies, 1955 (Oversize 6)
  - Montour Railroad: Bound ledger of financial data, 1913-1928 (Oversize 7)
  - Youngstown & Southern Railroad: Board of Directors meeting minutes, 1944-1979 (Oversize 8)
  - Pittsburgh, Chartiers, & Youghiogheny: Log of project reports, accounts, and expenditures, 1916-1981 (Oversize 9)
  - Daily reports of materials received, used, shipped, and released by P&LE lines, 1963 (Oversize 10)
  - Documents of planning for a Passenger Station at Woodlawn, PA (with correspondence, time estimates, materials inventories, general estimates, blueprints, cost analyses, etc., mostly concerning heating), 1917-1919 (Oversize 11)
  - Inventories of furniture and equipment; heating system valuations, 1913-1920 (Oversize 12)
  - Lake Erie & Eastern Railroad: ICC Bureau of Valuation land report with carrier's review, objections, and revisions, 1923-1926 (Oversize 13)
  - Report to ICC Bureau of Valuation by Pittsburgh and Ohio Valley Railroad, 1940-1952 (Oversize 14)
  - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings and magazine cutouts (Oversize 15)
  - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings and magazine cutouts (Oversize 16)
  - PLERR Train Yard, 1930; 1 photographs (Map-case 30-3, Folder 1)
    Gelatin Silver Panorama Print ca. 1930 taken from East Carson Street looking across the Monongahela River to Downtown Pittsburgh showing the PLERR trainyard and surrounding building.
  - Railroad scenes art prints, 1958-1959 (Map-case 30-3, Folder 2)
- Maps, Drawings and Plans, 1872-1990; XIV.; 593 items
  This series contains technical drawings, building plans and maps related to the activities of the Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad Company and its associates. The items in this series are housed either in map tubes or in oversized folders in map case drawers. Item level descriptions for materials in this series are available in a spreadsheet accessible in the Archives Service Center.
  - Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad Technical Drawings and Plans, 1889-1978; 1.
    - General drawings and plans (Roll 1)
    - General drawings and plans (Map-case 30-4, Folder 1)
    - Aliquippa (Map-case 30-4, Folder 2)
    - Beaver County (Map-case 30-4, Folder 3)
      - Jones & Laughlin Steel Mesh Fence, sheet 1, September 30, 1941
      - Jones & Laughlin Steel Mesh Fence, sheet 2, September 30, 1941
      - Jones & Laughlin Steel Mesh Fence, sheet 3, September 30, 1941
      - Jones & Laughlin Steel Mesh Fence, sheet 4, September 30, 1941
      - Jones & Laughlin Steel Mesh Fence, sheet 5, September 30, 1941
    - Beaver Falls (Map-case 30-4, Folder 4)
    - Beaver Falls/New Brighton (Map-case 30-4, Folder 5)
    - Connellsville (Map-case 30-4, Folder 6)
    - Fallston (Map-case 30-4, Folder 7)
    - Homestead Bridge, sheets 101-109AB (Map-case 30-4, Folder 8)
    - Homestead Bridge, sheets 109B-120 (Map-case 30-4, Folder 9)
    - Homestead Bridge, sheets 121-128, 201AB-205 (Map-case 30-4, Folder 10)
    - Homestead Bridge, sheets 206-218 (Map-case 30-4, Folder 11)
    - McKees Rocks (Map-case 30-5, Folder 1)
    - Newell (Map-case 30-5, Folder 2)
    - Pittsburgh (Map-case 30-5, Folder 3)
    - Pittsburgh Express Building (Map-case 30-5, Folder 4)
    - Pittsburgh Terminal Station, undated (Map-case 30-5, Folder 5)
    - West Homestead (Map-case 30-5, Folder 6)
    - Other Pennsylvania Locations, A-Z (Map-case 30-5, Folder 7)
    - Other Pennsylvania Locations, A-Z (Roll 2)
    - Ohio (Map-case 30-5, Folder 8)
  - Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad Property Maps, 1890-1971; 2.
    - By Location, A-Z (Map-case 30-5, Folder 9)
      - Aliquippa, April 26, 1923
      - Downer Branch Abandonment, November 19, 1946
      - Land for Union Railroad Company, December 3, 1968
      - Monaca Property, undated
      - National Tube Company, undated
      - Pittsburgh and Lake Erie Railroad, January 21, 1971
      - Pittsburgh District Industries, November 16, 1929
      - Pittsburgh Steel Hoop Company, April, 15, 1901
      - Schoen Steel Wheel Company, February 10, 1904
    - Right of way and track maps (Roll 3-18)
  - Other Railroad Companies, 1882-1990; 3.
    - Cleveland and Pittsburgh Railroad Company (Roll 19)
    - Lake Erie and Eastern Railroad Company (Roll 20)
    - Lewis Run Railway Company (Map-case 30-6, Folder 1)
    - Monongahela Connecting Railroad Company (Roll 21)
      - Blueprint map of tracks from the Pittsburgh, Virginia and Charleston Railway to the Hot Metal Bridge, including location of buildings of Jones & Laughlin's Pittsburgh Works, January 1, 1929; 1.
      - Blueprint map of South Yard, including location of buildings of Jones & Laughlin's Pittsburgh Works, January 1, 1929; 2.
      - Blueprint map of Twenty-second Street Yard, January 1, 1929; 3.
      - Blueprint map of tracks from the bridge to Thirty-fourth Street, January 1, 1929; 4.